<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PolMine Project</title>
    <description>Website of the PolMine Project</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 06:16:32 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 06:16:32 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Project 'Linking Textual Data' started. </title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;new-project-linking-textual-data-started&quot;&gt;New Project ‘Linking Textual Data’ started.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our newest project “Linking Textual Data” is part of the &lt;em&gt;Consortium for the Social, Behavioral, Educational and Economic Sciences&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.konsortswd.de/en/&quot;&gt;KonsortSWD&lt;/a&gt;) and contributes to the &lt;em&gt;National Research Data Infrastructure&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nfdi.de/en-gb&quot;&gt;NFDI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new project that has officially started on Januar 1st 2021, we develop tools for linking different data types in order to open up new avenues for research. Corpora have become an important data type in the social sciences. Methods for analysing text are developing rapidly. A crucial aspect of the huge potential of large-scale corpora for the social sciences are capabilities to link the analysis of text and other data types, such as surveys. Yet the barriers to data linkage are still high. The tools and workflows we will develop and share shall improve our abilities to gain new insights through the combination of different data types. Not surprisingly, corpora play a central role in our plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NFDI is the broader context of our endeavour. It aims to secure and utilize research data in a systematic and sustainable way. To reach this goal, the NFDI plans to establish the management of research data according to the “FAIR” principles. These principles mandate that research data are findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable for and by the scientific community. Furthermore, the NFDI aims to connect to international initiatives with similar aims such as the &lt;em&gt;European Open Science Cloud&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://eosc-portal.eu&quot;&gt;EOSC&lt;/a&gt;). The efforts of the NFDI are not limited to particular disciplines, they include consortia as diverse as chemistry, culture, health, engineering and many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the NFDI, the social sciences are represented through KonsortSWD. Specifically, KonsortSWD strengthens, widens and deepens a research data infrastructure for the social, educational, behavioural and economic sciences. Again, the FAIR principles offer guidance: KonsortSWD wants to provide the community (including research data centres) with adequate tools to share and manage data accordingly. Apart from community engagement, data access, ethics and technical solutions, another important task concerns the production of data. This is where our project is located. More specifically, our aim is to contribute to new insights by developing tools for data linkage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All efforts to utilize research data need to serve the community! Are there any best practices, opportunities and limits? What does the community need from such an infrastructure to be able to use it and profit from it? Community involvement is thus the key to successful data management. If you have any ideas or input how your projects could profit from “Linking Textual Data”, feel free to reach out to us.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/03/01/Linking-Textual-Data.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/03/01/Linking-Textual-Data.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>cwbtools v0.3.3 'Hemicycle' brings Europarl closer. </title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;cwbtools-v033-hemicycle-brings-europarl-closer&quot;&gt;cwbtools v0.3.3 ‘Hemicycle’ brings Europarl closer.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an immediate follow-up to cwbtools v0.3.2 “Il Postino”, a new cwbtools version (v0.3.3, “Hemicycle”) just made it to CRAN. This has become necessary to fix errors with the Solaris and Fedora test environments of CRAN that occurred because v0.3.2 expanded test coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes to meet CRAN requirements will not be relevant for most users. So why bother to install the new release? There is one nice new feature: Assumptions made by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;corpus_install()&lt;/code&gt;, the mechanism for installing corpora, have been relaxed as follows: The binary data directory in a corpus tarball may now also be named “data” (not only “indexed_corpora”) and binary files need not reside in a subdirectory named after the corpus. They can be in the data directory directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to two classic corpora - the Europarl corpus with debates in the European parliament and the Dickens corpus with Charles Dickens’ novels - is super-easy now: Simply use the following code to download and install both corpora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwbtoos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dickens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;http://cwb.sourceforge.net/temp/Dickens-1.0.tar.gz&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;corpus_install&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tarball&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dickens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;http://corpora.linguistik.uni-erlangen.de/demos/download/Europarl3-CWB-2010-02-28.tar.gz&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;corpus_install&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tarball&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second note on this release: The functionality that has evolved to install corpora from Web storage, from a repository such as Zenodo and from Amazon S3 supersedes previous ideas to ship (large) corpora in R data packages. The big disadvantage of using R data packages for data dissemination is the need to re-install corpora every time there is a major R update. So cwbtools v0.3.3 makes initial steps to declare functionality as deprecated that assists users to wrap corpora in packages. In this vein, the previous &lt;em&gt;Europarl&lt;/em&gt;-vignette that explained how to wrap the Europarl corpus into an R data package has been dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But functionality to download and install Europarl from the Web is there! A nice thing about Europarl is that it is a multilingual ressource, making it relevant for many international users. As a tribute to the European Parliament (EP), this release is labelled “Hemicycle”: This is how the plenary chamber of the EP at Strasbourg is called, following a tradition to arrange seats and parliamentary groups in a circular shape.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/23/cwbtools-v0.3.3-Hemicycle-install-Europarl-at-ease.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/23/cwbtools-v0.3.3-Hemicycle-install-Europarl-at-ease.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>cwbtools v0.3.2 'Il Postino' solidifies corpus download. </title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;rcppcwb-v032-il-postino-solidifies-corpus-download&quot;&gt;RcppCWB v0.3.2 ‘Il Postino’ solidifies corpus download.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new, previously unknown bug users reported when trying to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=GermaParl&quot;&gt;GermaParl&lt;/a&gt; package to download and install the GermaParl corpus (function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;germaparl_install_corpus()&lt;/code&gt;) generated some urgency to release of a new version of the cwbtools R package: We suddenly saw errors (false positives!) when checking whether GermaParl can be downloaded from Zenodo. A switch from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RCurl::url.exists()&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;httr::http_error()&lt;/code&gt; solves this small yet nasty problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second important bug fix is that it is now possible to encode more than one positional attribute at a time – without hacks. We are relieved that this limitation of the usefulness of cwbtools is overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But cwbtools v0.3.2 also brings new features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a corpus is downloaded from Zenodo, the md5 checksum is checked to ensure the integrity of the data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is now possible to download corpora from Amazon S3. This may be very useful for projects that cannot yet publish data publicly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So data delivery is more robust and more comprehensive. This is why the release is labelled ‘Il Postino’. To learn more about cwbtools v0.3.2 ‘Il Postino’, please consult the &lt;a href=&quot;https://polmine.github.io/cwbtools/news/index.html&quot;&gt;package changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the users who reported the issue that downloading GermaParl did not work, temporarily! Good news: Downloading GermaParl from Zenodo works again the way it should.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/17/cwbtools-v0.3.2-Il-Postino-solidifies-and-expands-corpus-download.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/17/cwbtools-v0.3.2-Il-Postino-solidifies-and-expands-corpus-download.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RcppCWB v0.3.2 'Dune Ride' ensures Apple Silicon compatibility. </title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;rcppcwb-v032-dune-ride-ensures-apple-silicon-compatibility&quot;&gt;RcppCWB v0.3.2 ‘Dune Ride’ ensures Apple Silicon compatibility.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple’s new M1 chip has deservedly raised significant attention. The new Mac minis and 13 inch Macbook Pros running on “Apple Silicon” are fast, energy-saving and affordable at the same time. No doubt an increasing number of polmineR users will work on an M1 machine. So we need to take care that everything works with the new generation of processors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, everything hinges on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://polmine.github.io/RcppCWB/&quot;&gt;RcppCWB&lt;/a&gt; package. The C code of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cwb.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;Corpus Workbench (CWB)&lt;/a&gt; included in the RcppCWB package and the C++ wrappers exposing CWB performance are the basis for everything that makes analysing corpora with polmineR fast. So the crucial question was whether RcppCWB would compile on M1 machines?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you run R with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosetta_(software)&quot;&gt;Rosetta&lt;/a&gt; emulator, everything is fine. But one issue arising with native M1 compiled code required our attention: If &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.gnome.org/glib/&quot;&gt;GLib-2.0&lt;/a&gt;, a dependency of the CWB, is not yet present, it would be downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PolMine/libglib/&quot;&gt;libglib&lt;/a&gt; repository we host with GitHub. And GLib binaries for the new processor architecture were not there yet. And RcppCWB, which had been developed assuming that every Mac has Intel inside, would not look for M1-compatible dependencies either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is solved with &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=RcppCWB&quot;&gt;RcppCWB v0.3.2&lt;/a&gt; which has just made its way to CRAN. The functionality of the package remains unchanged. Working on the configure script anyway, I tried to make it more robust and verbose so that users could get a better idea what is wrong when facing an issue when compiling the package. For instance, there is now a warning when &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcre.org/&quot;&gt;PCRE&lt;/a&gt; is present but has been compiled without Unicode support. Yet the primary focus of the new release is to ensure that RcppCWB (and polmineR, cwbtools etc) work seamlessly on the new Apple machines with M1 chips inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been achieved. Because it is just not possible to get one of the new machines really quickly (delivery takes a few weeks), we used a cloud solution offered by MacStadium to be able to adjust things and run tests now. This worked nicely, no complaints. Nevertheless, making the adjustments required some attention. This is why this release of RcppCWB is called “Dune Ride”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need further explanation? Dunes are made of sand, and processors are made of silicon, and silicon is made of sand, and so is the M1 chip, I guess, so rodeo with M1 is a dune ride, metaphorically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you face issues running RcppCWB/polmineR/cwbtools on M1, please use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PolMine/RcppCWB/issues&quot;&gt;RcppCWB issues&lt;/a&gt; to let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/04/RcppCWB-v0.3.2-Dune-Ride-Ensures-Apple-Silicon-Compatibility.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/02/04/RcppCWB-v0.3.2-Dune-Ride-Ensures-Apple-Silicon-Compatibility.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GermaParl v1.5.1 'Drunken Sailor' Released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;germaparl-v151-drunken-sailor-released&quot;&gt;GermaParl v1.5.1 ‘Drunken Sailor’ Released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=GermaParl&quot;&gt;GermaParl&lt;/a&gt; package is
back at CRAN. The most recent version (v1.5.1) that has just been
released is the first one I expect to pass all checks on all systems. If
nothing goes wrong, it will be the first fully portable version of the
GermaParl R package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the formular ‘less is more’ has been a precondition for that.
I guess the song &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drunken_Sailor&quot;&gt;“What Shall We Do with the Drunken
Sailor”&lt;/a&gt; is widely known:
How do you get somebody, who has enjoyed too much previously sober
again? Metaphorically, this is what GermaParl has gone through now.
Functions to add further annotation layers were actually quite generic
have been removed from the GermaParl package, they have been moved to
the (GitHub-only) package
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PolMine/polmineR.misc&quot;&gt;polmineR.misc&lt;/a&gt;. Remaining
dependencies on the data.table and the RcppCWB package have also been
removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GermaParl package still offers the documentation of the data and a
very convenient download mechanism for the full GermaParl corpus. That’s
one rationale for the CRAN release. But more importantly from a
technical point of view, it includes some sample data. A next step will
be to use the sample data included in the GermaParl package in the
polmineR package, which can thus be turned a leaner package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And GermaParl is a much leaner package now, too. GermaParl is not a
drunken sailor any more with a terrible hangover (superfluous functions
and dependencies). As I believe, the package is quite sober now. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/28/GermaParl-v1.5.1-Drunken-Sailor-Released.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/28/GermaParl-v1.5.1-Drunken-Sailor-Released.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>polmineR v0.8.4 'Unicorn Dream' Released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;polminer-v084-unicorn-dream-released&quot;&gt;polmineR v0.8.4 ‘Unicorn Dream’ Released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=polmineR&quot;&gt;polmineR&lt;/a&gt;
(v0.8.4) is available at CRAN. Why do I call this release “Unicorn
Dream”? A unicorn dream is much better than a Unicode nightmare…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The predominant focus of the new release is portability. CRAN checks for
Solaris reported an issue on Solaris that resulted from Unicode
characters in the package documentation. Removing Unicode characters
from all documentation objects shall solve this issue. Indeed, I am
really glad to see that &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.r-project.org/web/checks/check_results_polmineR.html&quot;&gt;CRAN check
results&lt;/a&gt;
report that polmineR can now be installed on Solaris without any
warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second encoding issue caused an ERROR on CRAN check machines. There is
a Debian check machine with a UTF-8859-15 encoding. Yet handling
encodings by polmineR had been based on the premise that Windows
installations will have a latin-1 encoding, and that macOS and Linux
distributions will have a UTF-8 encoding. This assumption was too strong
and resulted in the aforementioned error. The new polmineR version is
more liberal: Linux users are not confined to use UTF-8 any more. So if
you have a taste for ISO-8859-1 … go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third issue with portability and CRAN checks was that building the
package vignette required pandoc to be installed. But it isn’t on the
CRAN machines for macOS and Solaris, resulting in a warning. The
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;knit_print()&lt;/code&gt; method that usually returns a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;htmlwidget&lt;/code&gt; will now
return a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data.table&lt;/code&gt;, if pandoc is missing. Building and re-building
package vignettes will not yield a warning if pandoc is not present and
still result in a telling vignette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my big hope is that polmineR v0.8.4 is the most portable version of
the package. I hope we will see an agreeable “OK” for all CRAN check
machines when all tests have been performed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I do not really believe that I will never have a nightshift
again caused by encoding issues and problems to handle Unicode, naming
the new polmineR release “Unicorn Dream” expresses my (naive) hopes for
a bright future and that encoding issues were ghosts haunting me only in
the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/22/polmineR-v0.8.4-Unicorn-Dream-Released.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/22/polmineR-v0.8.4-Unicorn-Dream-Released.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>cwbtools v0.3.1 'Straight No Chaser' Released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;cwbtools-v031-straight-no-chaser-released&quot;&gt;cwbtools v0.3.1 ‘Straight No Chaser’ Released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cwbtools&quot;&gt;cwbtools&lt;/a&gt;
(v0.3.1) is available at CRAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single change I want to highlight here is that the polmineR package
is not a (weak) dependency of cwbtools any more. The initial thrust for
that was to contain negative effects if polmineR can not be built for a
platform. Issues are more tricky to handle as long as polmineR depends
on cwbtools and cwbtools depends (though weakly) on polmineR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have a clarified struture that - within the PolMine family of
packages - polmineR depends on cwbtools and cwbtools depends on RcppCWB.
That’s it, straight no chaser. And this explains the naming of the new
release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding the polmineR dependency required replacing usage of some
high-level polmineR functions by lower-level functionality of the
RcppCWB package. Functions and unit tests have been re-written
accordingly. There is no change visible for the user. The only visible
changes concern some minor improvements of the user dialogues, see the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://polmine.github.io/cwbtools/news/index.html&quot;&gt;cwbtools changelog&lt;/a&gt;
if you are interested in the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking into the future, cwbtools v0.3.1 prepares an upcoming release of
the GermaParl package. This package will offer download functionality to
install GermaParl from Zenodo (an open science data repository used for
depositing PolMine corpora), and it includes a small subset of GermaParl
for testing purposes. While the download functionality is not strictly
necessary (it is just a thin wrapper for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cwbtools::corpus_install()&lt;/code&gt;),
the sample data within the package shall be very useful to make polmineR
a leaner package that can rely on the GermaParl package for sample data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of dependencies we aim at will then be: polmineR depends
on GermaParl and cwbtools, GermaParl depends on cwbtools, and cwbtools
(as well as polmineR) depends on RcppCWB. So this will be a structure
without any circularity. The current cwbtools release v0.3.1 “Straight
No Chaser” has prepared exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/21/cwbtools-v0.3.1-Straight-No-Chaser-Released.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/21/cwbtools-v0.3.1-Straight-No-Chaser-Released.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>cwbtools v0.3.0 'Apple Picker' Released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;cwbtools-v030-apple-picker-released&quot;&gt;cwbtools v0.3.0 ‘Apple Picker’ Released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cwbtools&quot;&gt;cwbtools&lt;/a&gt;
(v0.3.0) is available via CRAN and I do not want to miss explaining what
is new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the major &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; feature is that it is now possible to
download the tarball with a CWB indexed corpora from a server and to
install corpus files to the general corpus storage. The whereabouts of a
corpus can also be stated via a Document Object Identifier (DOI),
i.e. there is a new argument &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;doi&lt;/code&gt; for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;corpus_install()&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, resolving the DOI to get the URL of the corpus tarball is
implemented for DOIs issued by &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/&quot;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt; (using the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=zen4R&quot;&gt;zen4R&lt;/a&gt; package, which is a
new dependency). Zenodo is an open science repository hosted by CERN.
Several corpora prepared in the PolMine Project have been published with
Zenodo recently. As a result, it has never been easier and more reliable
to install corpora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3831472#.XxFLfB1CRZ0&quot;&gt;the United Nations General Assembly (UNGA)
corpus&lt;/a&gt;, use this
function call:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&quot;cwbtools&quot;) # cwbtools v0.3.0 required
corpus_install(doi = &quot;10.5281/zenodo.3831472&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, further corpora that have been prepared in the PolMine
Project available at Zenodo are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3742113#.XxFLnR1CRZ0&quot;&gt;GermaParl&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3819374#.XxFLrx1CRZ0&quot;&gt;ParisParl&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3819505#.XxFLwR1CRZ0&quot;&gt;AustroParl&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3835540#.XxFL2x1CRZ0&quot;&gt;RegioParl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3872263#.XxFL7x1CRZ0&quot;&gt;MigParl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usability of Zenodo for depositing data is outstanding. As a DOI is
issued upon uploading data, the service is comfortable and appropriate
for scientific data at the same time. So we think that Zenodo is a very
good option to establish the accessibility of corpora (in line with FAIR
principles). It is perfectly open for anybody who wants to publish data.
The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cwbtools::corpus_install()&lt;/code&gt; will work to download &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; tarball
with a CWB indexed corpus from Zenodo. Preparing and uploading the
tarballs is not difficult at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning usability, user dialogues in the cwbtools package have been
reworked thoroughly. We started to use the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cli&quot;&gt;cli&lt;/a&gt; package to create a better
command line interface. Beyond a nicer appearance and more informative
messages, user dialogues that will guide a user through the installation
of a corpus have been rewritten and extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a new strong support to store corpora in the system corpus
storage. If the respective directory structure is not yet present, the
user will be guided through the process of creating all directories that
are needed. Last but not least, defining the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CORPUS_REGISTRY&lt;/code&gt; variable
in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.Renviron&lt;/code&gt; file is supported by a user dialogue, so that corpora
are available across sessions without further ado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is quite some work that has gone into the new release of cwbtools.
But I am quite confident that the user experience may be much better
than before. As always, we will be happy to learn about your experiences
and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final remark. Why is this release called “Apple Picker”? cwbtools
v0.3.0 is about making downloading and installing corpora as comfortable
as possible. I thought that an apple picker was a nice metaphor for
that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/10/cwbtools-v0.3.0-Apple-Picker-Released.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/10/cwbtools-v0.3.0-Apple-Picker-Released.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RcppCWB v0.3.0 'Sunrise' Released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;rcppcwb-v030-sunrise-released&quot;&gt;RcppCWB v0.3.0 ‘Sunrise’ Released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We happily announce that RcppCWB v0.3.0 is available at CRAN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of the binaries for Windows and macOS users may still take a few days. But admittedly, this release is not about Windows and macOS, it is about Linux and Solaris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first major modification of RcppCWB v0.3.0 concerns the configure script. It know checks systematically whether dependencies (ncurses, glib-2.0, pcre) are present and will issue a telling error message when requirements are not met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the quick fix of RcppCWB v0.2.10 to use the ‘-fcommon’ flag to avoid GCC 10 errors with multiple includes has been dropped and replaced with a proper and durable solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global variables in the original CWB C code that GCC 10 would detect to be defined several times because of multiple includes have been turned to external variables.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A newly written header file provides the definition that satisfies the compiler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRAN pushed me hard in this direction. But they are perfectly right to do so: GCC 10 and its dislike of multiple tentative definitions is not yet very common (a Fedora phenomenon at this stage). But it is just a matter of time to become the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only changes in the R code of the package are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The dynamic library is unloaded when the package is unloaded. This is good practice and it was overdue to adopt it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CQP is initialized by default upon loading the package.  Among others, this should make it easier to implement a failsafe functionality in the cwbtools package for test loading CWB corpora.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the NEWS.md file for further minor updates and modifications in the package, such as compiler warnings that have been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, CRAN pushed me forcefully to implement the changes I have sketched quickly and to remove remaining “bashisms”. But it is well taken that if we want your package to be on CRAN, portability and quality are standards CRAN rightfully enforces. Checking the package across systems with different configurations is not really the fun part of developing a package. The hardest part is to ensure the portability for Solaris. I am quite sure I am not the only one who thinks it is tricky and mind wrecking work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because some aspects of preparing this release have been a nightmare and because I just saw that the package check status for Solaris is “OK”, I named this release “Sunrise”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is something that does not work, that needs improvement or that is in need of better documentation, please use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PolMine/RcppCWB/issues&quot;&gt;GitHub issues of the RcppCWB package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/09/RcppCWB-v0.3.0-Sunrise-Released.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/07/09/RcppCWB-v0.3.0-Sunrise-Released.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reuniting the PolMine family</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;reuniting-the-polmine-family&quot;&gt;Reuniting the PolMine family&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new version of RcppCWB (v0.2.10) just made it to CRAN. Updates of polmineR and cwbtools are about to follow. Among others, the new versions will offer more performance and a better user experience: The download mechanism of the cwbtools package has been reworked thoroughly and the polmineR package will use the buttons of the DataTable JavaScript library, leading to workflows that are much more intuitive for exporting data than the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;store()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mail()&lt;/code&gt; methods originally included in the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, putting things this way involves a good deal of whitewashing. The past days brought tons of unexpected hard work to prepare the releases caused by an unexpected meltdown of the PolMine presence at GitHub. Users must have been wondering what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offspring of all calamities was a harmless CRAN message that RcppCWB would not compile on Fedora 32 which uses GCC10. I do not know any polmineR user who uses Fedora, but the matter needed to be fixed. Fedora is a forerunner to use the latest compilers. It is just a matter of time that Debian and Ubuntu will move to GCC10 too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I submitted the new RcppCWB version two days before deadline CRAN hat set. Having run extensive checks of the new version, I was very confident that the package was addressing all issues CRAN had informed me about appropriatly. That assumption was perfectly true. But there was one more thing. A newly introduced test to prevent the usage of bash scripts and “bashisms” triggered the CRAN checks for incoming packages to fail. RcppCWB was archived. All dependencies of RcppCWB (polmineR and cwbtools) were archived. The PolMine suite of packages gone with the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where we stand: RcppCWB is back at CRAN for a few days. But when preparing the new releases of polmineR and cwbtools, all kinds of new CRAN checks and tests made one rework after another necessary. So I learned the tough way that the CRAN team is implementing policies in a much stricter manner than when I submitted the packages first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it made my life miserable the past days, I highly appreciate what the CRAN team does. It s a great safeguard to maintain the quality and portability of CRAN-publshed packages. It helps to make our packages better and more reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users have started to depend on the presence of RcppCWB, polmineR and cwbtools at CRAN. A couple of university courses use the packages and students may find it very frustrating that tools are not there, just as researchers. The current situation violates my own standards and what I want to achieve. So I really do apologize for the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do in the meantime? Releases of the new packages are finalized and are awaiting approval to re-appear at CRAN. It’s just just a little PolMine-CRAN ping pong we need to endure. To offer a convenient installation mechanism, PolMine’s CRAN-style drat repository at GitHub can be used. Please proceed as follows to get polmineR and cwbtools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;drat&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 'drat' package needed to access drat repository easily&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;addRepo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;polmine&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# PolMine in lower case here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;polmineR&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;cwbtools&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cautionary note: Older R versions are difficult to get but necessary to prepare binary versions for outdated R versions. So if you want to download binary packages for Windows and macOS, R version 4.0 may be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe me, I have learned my lesson. And everything we just experienced is a very strong stimulous for me to improve further to offer a suite of packages for the analysis of textual data that is as reliably there as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/06/30/Reuniting-the-PolMine-family.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/06/30/Reuniting-the-PolMine-family.html</guid>
        
        <category>news</category>
        
        
        <category>Posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
